Hi, Everyone.
This is S.Codes.
In just a few hours,
You will be able to biuld
this incredible app from scratch.
And add it to your porfolio.
Besides, this course is completely free.
You will find all the links in the comments
to help you get started.
In this tutorial we will cover all aspects of frontend development with NextJs
In others words, we'll start from a figma template;
and you will learn how to transform your figma design into NextJs code using TailwindCss.
You will also learn how to organize and structure your project in a logical way.
to keep your code base maintainable.
From there, you will learn how to create reusable, functional React components
with Tailwind Css, ShadCn and Framer Motion.
We'll be using Typescript for type checking
to ensure the correctness of your react components.
Ad also Eslint to check and fix syntax errors.
Managing React global state can be tricky, that's why we will be using Redux toolkit
Which is the most popular state management library
to manage the state of your NextJs application.
Additionnaly, you wil learn how to monitor and test your code using jest
React testing library and Cypress.
Finally, we'll commit our code to the repository and deploy our app to Vercel.
Before diving into Next.js
Let's make sure that you have prerequisites.
You need to have a solid understanding of fundamental web development concepts.
Including HTML, CSS, Javascript.
Whether you're new to React, Next.js or not.
It doesn't matter,
i'm going to give you all the details you need in this course.
Next.js is a Javascript framework.
Which means, Next is made of Javascript.
It needs to run in a Javascript environment and that kind of environment is called Node.js
Node.js is an open source cross platform Javascript runtime environment.
To install this environment on your computer
you actually need to download a pakage that is available from the nodejs.org website.
This package will install the Javascript environment and also something called npm.
NPM is a node package manager.
Which refers to a software repository, but it's also a place where developers can find, build and manage Javascript packages.
Currently, NPM contains over 800,000 packages for various Javascript applications so enjoy it.
Next.js is a flexible React framework that gives you building blocks to create fast full stack web applicaion
But what exactly does that mean ?
First of all you need to understand the word "web application".
A web application also known as a web app is nothing more than a computer program
that uses a web browser to perform a specific function.
A web app is a client-server program that has a client side and a server side.
On the one hand, client side refers to everything in a web application that is displayed or takes place on the client.
This includes what the use sees such as text, images and the rest of the user interface.
The client side, it's also known as the Frontend, although these two terms do not mean exactly the same thing.
Client side refers only to the location where processes run.
While Frontend refers to the types of processes that run on the client side.
On the other hand, server side refers to everything that happens on the server instead of the client.
It refers to applications that run on the server side.
And this includes:
rendering dynamic web pages,
interactive with databases,
authentification and push notifications.
Now, we are going to create a new project,
So, go to Nextjs.org
copy this command
open your terminal
cd to the folder where you want to keep your project.
And run the following  command
Now open your project.
We will use npm run dev to start your nextjs development server.
Then go to localhost:3000 in your browser.
Your home page should look like this, which is intentionally unstyled:
You should navigate to the comments to see the necessary links
Select the repo link
to access to project git repository.
Then scroll down to the README section.
and find title code organization and folder structure.
You'll see the project tree and description of each project folder and subfolder.
It's very clear and easy to understand.
For now i'm just going to give you a brief description of each folder.
When you install a nextjs 14 app, you will have a empty project with defaults folders like .next folder
This is generated folder that contains the output of the nextjs build process.
You usually don't need to touch this folder directly.
The app folder, this is the main NextJs 14 folder.
You can edit all pages and API routes in this folder.
The node_modules directory, this directory houses all third party libraries adn dependencies for your app.
Public folder, it contains all static assets for your application such as images.
You'll also notice configurations files in the root of your applicaion.
Most of theses files are created and pre-configured you start a new project with the create-next-app.
We have the Eslint file, this file is for Eslint configuration.
The .gitignore file is used to specify intentionally untracked files that git should ignore.
Also, nextjs.config file is the NextJs configuration file.
The package.json is a Metadata file in a Node Js project that describes the project dependencies, scripts, configurations and other details.
The package lock is automatically generated for all operations where npm modifies either the node_modules tree or package.json.
The post.config is the post css configuration file.
Post Css is a language for transforming Css code, i mean it will convert our Tailwind Css code
into something that most browsers can understand.
The README file is a text file that introduces and explain the project.
Tailwind Css config is a file where we should define our Tailwind configuration like theme, breakpoints and more.
Finally, the tsconfig file is a configuration file for Typescript project.
It specifies the compiler option needed to compile the project.
Now we actually need to create new folders in our project.
For instance, we will create a folder called actions.
This folder contains asynchronous functions that run on the server.
They can be called in server in client componentsto handle form submission and data mutation.
Woah, what do you mean by server in client component and what is data mutation ?
Well, if you clearly understood client-server concepts i've just explained  earlieryou would already know that.
A server component is a component that is obviously going to be rendered on the server.
And it would be the same for a client component.
Just keep in mind that every time you create a component in NextJs, it would be either a client or server component.
Knowing whether you are using a client or server component  is very easy.
By default, Next.js always uses server components, this allows you to automatically implement server rendering with no additionnal configuration.
And you can opt to use client component when needed by adding the react use client directive at the top of the file above your imports
We'll make a directory _tests_
This is where Jest will used to look up test
We'll also make a directory called components